# Camilo Cabrera

Data Scientist, Analytics Professional, MSc in Operations Research and Productivy Enthusiast

cecabrera55@gmail.com

# Summary

camicabrera.com

Master of Science in Industrial Engineering (Operations Research and Statistics) from Universidad de los Andes in Bogotá.

Data Scientist, Analytics Professional, Statistician and Operations Researcher. Currently in Colombia.

Camilo is working as an Analytics Consultant in Fidelio Digital S.A.S. planning, structuring, financing and executing major Business Intelligence and Business Analytics projects for clients. He has developed projects with the Colombian government to read, preparate, analize and publish statistical data for citizens.

Camilo worked as Chief Analytics Officer leading analytical (Business Intelligence and Machine Learning) solutions for the Colombian industry. He used open-source languages like R, Python, PostgreSQL, MySQL and D3 to deploy reports and make research on in-house operations and with clients. He implied a 40% investment saving in tools and human resources throughout reporting.

He worked in Brasil as Big Data Analyst for eCGlobal: marketing research multi-national company. Through survey and social media analysis he delivered insights focused on marketing investment optimization in multi-national retail and entertainment companies in Latin America. He used commercial softwares (Tableau) and open-source technologies (R, MongoDB and PostgreSQL) to deploy results.

He worked as consultant in operations research in Offshore Oil & Gas industry delivering reports focused on pressure dynamics due to hydrocarbons extraction in Colombian' Pacific Ocean.

# Experience

Analytics Consultant January 2018 - Present

Planning, structuring, financing and executing Business Intelligence and Business Analytics projects with clientes.

#### **Independent Analytics Contractor**

#### June 2017 - Present

Independent Contractor in planning, funding and executing Analytical and Bussiness Intelligence projects with clients. Currently working for Huila's Government on the deployment of their open data platform.

### Chief Analytics Officer at IKONOSOFT

June 2016 - May 2017 (1 year)

- \* Company's business intelligence manager.
- \* Business unit manager called Ikognitive.
- \* Development of commercial reports in real time to General Manager. 40% saving in reporting and BI tools.

#### **Data Analysis Contractor**

November 2016 - December 2016 (2 months)

Data Analyst and Contractor in the Regional Information System (SIR) in Huila department in Colombia. Diagnosis and recommendations made related to local data management and information gathering.

#### Big Data Analyst at eCGlobal Solutions / eCMetrics

May 2015 - April 2016 (1 year)

- Social Media (Twitter and Facebook) monitoring using Tableau, R, Python and MongoDB. Outputs: Contingency Tables, Bubble Charts, Principal Components Analysis, Correspondence Analysis and Correlograms. Examples availables at LinkedIn profile.
- Survey's Contingency Tables (crosstabs) and Perceptual Maps using R and PostgreSQL.
- Intensity: Full time.

## Graduate Coordinator in Industrial Engineering at Universidad de los Andes

March 2013 - December 2014 (1 year 10 months)

 Hiring and training 19 tutor students to support 200 first semester students in their adaptation process at Universidad de los Andes. Each tutor was trained on public presentation, time management, leadership, teamwork, programming language and differential calculus. Intensity: 24 hours per week.

#### Consultant and Researcher

May 2014 - July 2014 (3 months)

- Consultant on the development and identification of offshore oil industry of pressure dynamic's components.
- Researcher in international experiences for Strategic Environmental and Social Assessment in the Pacific Region in Colombia. Guidelines and strategies were proposed for environmental sustainability.

• Intensity: Full time.

## Tutor of Programa de Acompañamiento at Universidad de los Andes September 2010 - May 2013 (2 years 9 months)

Program for freshmen students of Industrial Engineering to facilitate academic, social and psychological splicing to college life. The program is to enact complementary subjects such as "Algorithms and Programming", "Integral Calculus", "Differential Calculus" and "Pre-Calculus" classes. Intensity: 6 hours per week.

#### Market Risk Intern at CorpBanca

January 2012 - July 2012 (7 months)

- Calculating and presenting daily P&G operations in financial derivatives (swaps and forwards) and fixed income (bonds) using Visual Basic for Microsoft Excel to accelerate the results delivery, achieving improvements up to 60% in report generation time.
- Chosen as "Employee of the Month" in June, 2012. Intensity: Full time.

## Education

Universidad de Los Andes

Master's Degree, Operations Research, 2013 - 2014

Universidad de Los Andes

Engineer's degree, Industrial Engineering, 2008 - 2013

Activities and Societies: Universidad de los Andes, Bogotá. Relevant Courses: Business Valuation, Finance, Capital Markets, Principles of Optimization, Discrete Event Simulation, Mathematical Models in Financial Management, Organizational Strategy and System Dynamics.

# Camilo Cabrera

Data Scientist, Analytics Professional, MSc in Operations Research and Productivy Enthusiast

cecabrera55@gmail.com



Contact Camilo on LinkedIn